Guide to the Margaret Strickland Papers 1880-1970 MSS 077
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Margaret Strickland Papers
1880-1970
MSS 077
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
4.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
The Margaret Strickland Papers are a diverse collection of materials featuring the original typescripts of Strickland's biographical works, novels, plays, short stories, and short non-fiction works, as well as correspondence, hand-written and illustrated magazines, diaries, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Provenance
The collection was purchased from James Burmester in 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival materials.
BOX 3 has been removed for preservation treatment and is not currently available to resarchers.
Biographical Note
Margaret Strickland (born c. 1880) was a prolific writer of magazine stories and novels for adults and children. The majority of this collection comprises original typescripts of her adult stories; these are often of a romantic nature, usually involving the upper and middle classes and sometimes incorporating a touch of mystery or suspense. Also included are a typescript and a synopsis from her series of Michael Gerahty detective novels for children. She appears to have been reasonably well known, with interest in her work being shown from abroad (one letter refers to American serial rights, another requests translation rights for a Javian magazine). She had an obvious love of animals-her children's stories usually feature almost human animals-and her other passions included gardening and crossword puzzles, which she compiled for various newspapers.
Margaret Strickland was a great niece of the famous literary Strickland sisters. Her grandfather, Thomas Strickland, was the youngest brother of Agnes, Jane and Elizabeth Strickland, and Catherine Traill. Agnes was the best known of the family and is remembered for her monumental work, The Lives of the Queens of England (1840-48). Margaret suggests that Thomas was viewed as the black sheep of the family, and he was barely mentioned in either of the biographies of Agnes Strickland. Several of Thomas' siblings, including Catherine and another brother, Samuel, immigrated to Canada, where Catherine wrote a number of books and novels and Samuel founded the city of Lakeside.
Margaret had two sisters, both noted for their ability in drawing animals and staid, country scenes. Agnes Strickland is still remembered for her botanical illustrations, and Diana Mary (later Mrs. Mallet Veale) moved to Rhodesia and became well known for her illustrations of native life. Early examples of the artistic work by these talented sisters include twelve issues of the Illustrated Amateur Magazine, a small 'publication' Margaret created with her sisters from 1897-1899.
Little of Margaret's personal life is revealed in this collection, although a quantity of love letters, probably written in c. 1900, indicate a serious love affair with "Louis"; she later married Richard Hugh Worley on the 19th of October, 1908.
Scope and Content Note
The Margaret Strickland Papers are a diverse collection of materials featuring the original typescripts of Strickland's biographical works, novels, plays, short stories, and short non-fiction works, as well as correspondence, hand-written and illustrated magazines, diaries, scrapbooks, and photographs. The collection is divided into six series.
Arrangement
Collection materials have been arranged into six series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Manuscripts, (3) Illustrated Amateur Magazine, (4) Scrapbooks and Diaries, (5) Personal materials, and (6) Photographs. Series 2 represents the most substantial portion of the collection and contains 4 subseries: (A) Biographical works, (B) Novels, (C) Plays, and (D) Short fiction and non-fiction works. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Strickland, Agnes, 1796-1874; Strickland, Margaret, 1880-1940; Correspondence.; Diaries.; England |v Juvenile fiction.; England.; English fiction |y 19th century.; English literature.; Illustrations.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Short stories |z England |y 19th century.; Typescripts.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence-General, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-Louis, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-Louis, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Louis, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Regarding Strickland's work, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence-Wosley, Richard, (Strickland's Husband)., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II Manuscripts
  - Subseries A: Biographical Works
    - He Sought Not Fame, Chap. I-XIV, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - He Sought Not Fame, Chap. XV-XXXVII, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - He Sought Not Fame, copy 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - He Sought Not Fame, Chap. XV-XXXVII, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Traill, Mrs. Catherine Parr. History and Genealogical notes of the Strickland family. With notes by Margaret Strickland., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Novels
    - Called Away, Chap. I-XI, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Called Away, Chap. XII-XX, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Called Away, Author's Manuscript Cover, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Crouching Shadow, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - The Michael Gerahty Case, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Michael Gerahty Case, alternate version, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Michael Gerahty Case, synopsis, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Michael Gerahty Case, royalty statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Mystery of "Curling Water", Chap. I-XIX, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Mystery of "Curling Water", Chap. XX-XXXIII, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Mystery of "Curling Water", Author's Manuscript Cover, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Personality of Flowers, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Wildenhall Story, Chap. I-XVIII, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - The Wildenhall Story, Chap. XIX-XLIV, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - The Wildenhall Story, Chap. XLV-LXIX, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Wildenhall Story, letter of apology for length of manuscript., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified "Part II" of a novel, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries C: Plays
    - A Case for Divorce, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The Case of Lottie Bursall, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - A Pair of Gloves, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Strife of Tongues, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Short Stories and Short Non-Fiction Works
    - "The Advertisement", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Aspidistra", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Because of Stripey", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Blue Peristola", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "The Bogey-Man", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Bone Heads", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "A Brief for the Cat", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "A Brief for the "Common Cold", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Buying His Chance", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "By Stealth", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "The Calling Eyes", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "The Carpet", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Carte Blanche", undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Case of Lottie Bursall", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Cats-and Gardens", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Cheats", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "The Chink in the Armour", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Cupid's Night Out", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "The Curious Behavior of Seeds", undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "The Curse of Judith Thorne", undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Dark Horses", undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Dido Speaking", undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "The Feud", undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Five Animal Short Stories", undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "The Flight", undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "The Furniture", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "The Gate-Crasher", undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Giving Jim His Chance", undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "The Goad of Memory", undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "The Good-Man of this House", undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Gommie's Jubilee Binge", undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "The Green Eyes of Beppe", undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Gussie", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "The Hamper", undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "Her Lucky Day", undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Her 'Unknown'", undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "It Is Not Only Elephants Who Remember", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "The Leopard Skin", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - The London Spice Box, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "The Maroon Robe", undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "The Miniature", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "The Modern Kid", undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "More Than Coronets", undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "The Mummy Hand", undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "Not the Same", undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "Odd Fish", undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Of All the Queer Chances! Chap. I-X, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Of All the Queer Chances! Chap. XI-XVIII, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "The Ogre Next Door", undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "Our Friendly Garden Herbs", undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "Perchance to Dream", undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "The Porch of Wrong", undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Posh Coat", undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Queer Pets", undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "The Question", undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "A Question of Colour", undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "Red Murder!", undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "The Ring", undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Romany Doctor", undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "'Simples' Not to Be Despised", undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "The Story of a Wasp", undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "The Tarantula", undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "The Thug", undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "The Trap", undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - "Traveling Companions", undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - "Twelve Uncanny Stories", undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "The Wayfarer", undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "While Margot Slept", undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "Wise Birds and Kind Birds", undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "The Woman Who Knew Too Much", undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - "Woman's Inconsistency", undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Unidentified Fragments of Short Works, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Series III: Illustrated Amateur Magazine
  Separated Materials note
  BOX 3 has been removed for preservation treatment.
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 1, no. 1, 10, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 1, no. 2, 11, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 1, no. 3, 12, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 1, no. 4, 1, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 1, no. 5, 3, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 1, 7, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 2, 8, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 3, 9, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 4, 10, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 5, 11, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 2, no. 6, 12, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Illustrated Amateur Magazine, vol. 3, no. 1, 12, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Diaries and Scrapbooks
  - Book of Poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Diary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Diary, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series V: Personal Materials
  - Centenary Exhibition Catalogue for Queens of England by Agnes Strickland, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Personal, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Publishing Contract with Angold's Limited, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Royal Horticultural Society Awards, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Strickland, Agnus-Cartoon, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Strickland Family Crest, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Strickland Family Tree, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Toynbee, William. Song-Words. With letter from author., undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Wedding Announcement and Wedding Invitation, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
- OVERSIZE Series IV: Diaries and Scrapbooks
  - Photo Album, undated (Box Oversize)
- OVERSIZE Series V: Personal Materials
  - Local Examinations in Music Certificate, Trinity College London, June 1890 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Local Examinations Senior Grade Pass Certificate, The Associated Board of the Royal Academy of Music & The Royal College of Music, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "A New Card Game, 'The Sport of Kings' or 'King of Sports': List of some Derby Winners & Their Jockeys", circa 1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- OVERSIZE Series VI: Photographs
  - Group Photograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Wedding Photograph by G. Herrett, Brentwood, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - West Wratting Park the House, Group Photograph, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Young Male Sports Team Photograph: "Mr. Warley Brawley, Oxford 41", undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - West Wratting Park House, Group Photograph by R.H. Lord, Cambridge, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Male Dinner Party Photograph by R.H. Lord, Cambridge, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - October Term - Male Dinner Party Photograph, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Nude in Nature Photograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)